In today's video, we're going to talk
about Italian ice, shaved ice, slushies,
snow cones, and all those kind of
things. And we're going to do a machine
review,
too. So, yeah, ice. There's lots of
different names and not as many types.
So, you know the kind of things I'm
talking about when you go to a fair or
something like that and you get a paper
cup with shaved ice in the top with a
syrup drizzled over the top. These are
the kind of things on the screen now
that I'm talking about. There's really
only one type back in the UK and that
was Mr. Frosty. That was the original
name for a little machine. I'll put a
picture on screen now. I mean, we're
talking 40 years ago plus here, but
essentially it was a slushie. That
That's what it was. It was ice that was
somewhere between shaved and crushed.
And then you'd pour the syrups over the
top and that was it. And in those syrups
is various ingredients, natural and
artificial. Always has been, always will
be. So that's kind of what I grew up as
a young kid experiencing. In the US, you
have your snow cones and your shaved ice
as well. You have Hawaiian shaved ice.
So, you know, there's lots of different
things.
What are they and what are the
differences? So, a snow cone is ice that
has been crushed but actually isn't
shaved. It's crushed into smaller pieces
and then molded generally into a bowl
and then put into a serving container.
Generally, from what I can gather, a
cone, paper cone or card cone. So, your
shaved ice which is from
Hawaii/Japan. That's the origin of
shaved ice. And blades will shave the
ice off into a much finer, softer
snowextured kind of product. So having
one called snow cone and the other one
called shaved ice. But actually in
reality, the shaved ice is more like
snow and the snow cone is more like ice.
So bit odd. But either way, it it's
pretty much all labeled under one term
in another country, Italian ice.
Just to confuse matters even more,
Italian ice is a generic term. People
think it's something specific. It's not.
It's a generic term for an ice drink,
slushie, or serving. So, it could be a
snow cone. It could be shaved ice. It
could be um almost sorbet or granita.
That's essentially what the Italian ice
circle of life is.
Traditionally, they would make it back
in Italy in a machine similar to an ice
cream machine. So, they would add the
flavors and get this the freezing point
right and then, you know, spin it or
whip it as some people like to call it
on Wikipedia. You're not whipping
anything. You're just churning and c
you're freezing that mix into whatever
you want it to be. So, you know, you can
think of sorbes and granitas are pretty
much like snow cones as well. They're
just a different texture. A sorbet is a
softer, much finer ice crystal than a
grrenita. And a granita is again very
similar to a snow cone. Super confusing.
Anyway, Viva have sponsored this video
and they have sent a machine to me. It
was sent for free for review. I am not
going to be kind on this machine if it's
crap. So, let's get it unboxed and see
what it
is. So, there we go. Machine
unboxed. Ice catching tray. It's a good
size. I mean, it's
huge, especially for one person. Let's
This is called an ice crusher, but
actually when you look online, it all it
says ice shaver. I don't know what it
is, whether it's an ice crusher or an
ice shaver. I'd
say by I'm going show you what I'm
talking about here. By looking inside
here, these blades to me dictate that it
is a shaver rather than a
crusher. Specs of the machine. So, this
is 300 W pulling 2.6
amps. This case is
plastic. So, is that stainless steel
stainless steel handle, rubber grip that
I thought that would be rigid, but it's
not. That's totally flexible. So, I
wonder what the point of that little
thing is cuz that's not going to do
anything.
Caution, be care of
finger. Under here is where the ice will
come out. So that is obviously a power
button. A lot of plastic on this. I
thought it would be heavier.
Everything's made of plastic.
Okay. And what do we have here? This is
our instruction. And here, see? So on
the on the top here, it's called ice
crusher. Looking at the screen. On the
top here, it's called ice
crusher. On the instruction manual, it's
called an ice shaver.
Instructions are what they are. I'm not
going to read those. What do we have in
here? I'm going to assume that this
is some more
blades. Super
sticky. Oh, one
blade. Well, that's fine if only one
blade goes down. Having four spare
blades. There's four blades in the head
would be much better. So capacity of
this
machine capacity of the machine is
apparently up to and including 85 kilos
of ice per
hour. Don't know that sounds like a lot.
The machine is suitable for shaving
small ice cubes with a side length of no
more than 2 to 3 cm. Large ice will
cause machine to jam or even burn out
the motor.
So that's a downside because in a
commercial environment to make shaved
ice they use large pieces of ice, you
know, big either rounds or squares
depending on the machine that you use.
And you put that whole thing in and a
blade shaves it down really nice and you
get that super fine snowlike texture.
But as we're going to be made to use
small pieces of ice in this, I'm going
to stick my finger in it.
All right, the blades are secure. Um, as
we're going to be putting small bits of
ice in there, I don't know what the
resulting texture is going to be. Let's
turn it
on. It's not too
loud. Not too bad. So, we've got our ice
shaver crusher machine, our bowl, which
I'm not going to use. Actually, no, I
will use it. Let me clean the bowl
first.
Get rid of
that syrups. That is what you flavor
these ice desserts with. Um, you can buy
lots of different types of varying
qualities, but ultimately they're all
the same thing. They are a concentrated
sugar syrup with real or artificial
flavors. So, you can go for something
sugar-free, thin chocolate, caramel,
mateos. I hate that stuff in coffee.
pistachio, monin, all monin syrups will
work for this and they're really good
because monin is a very good quality
product. So pistachio
uh amarina fabri you know this is
possibly the best quality syrup on the
market by the way. Vanilla only if you
want to make vanilla rice
VIP let's kick it French raspberry and
then peppermint. This is gonna feature
in my Starbucks Frappuccino video, which
is coming next week, by the way. So,
these are all reduced, some heavily
reduced, some thicker than others. So,
this is quite a thin one, relatively
speaking. This is a thick one here. Um,
any of these will work 100%. Just Just
choose your syrup carefully. I'm not
here to to dictate what you should or
shouldn't eat. I eat ice cream
all the time. That's uh There you go.
But this one is much better quality. So
this is sugar which is sugar and wild
cherry juice. Uh water, citric acid,
vegetable and fruit concentrate
preparations which include water, invert
sugar, carrot, black currant, citric
acid, and an artificial flavor. That is
much better quality than that one. But
here we go. So, I think before we keep
jammering on, let's get some ice
and do some crushing
slashshaving. In goes our ice. Turn the
machine
on. And
go. Man, that
uh that does not seal very well.
Jeez. So that just threw it everywhere
over the
counter. The the actual vessel for
holding the
ice is
junk. There's a huge gap around the top.
Let me show you. Huge gap around the
top. So as you push that
down, all that happens is it comes
barreling out the top here rather than
down into there. So, also something else
to note, this was described as a shaver.
It 100% isn't. This is a crusher. You
can see the size of the crystals there.
Quite large. So, they need to decide on
what it is that they're
selling. Let's put some in a better
bowl. Let's say this
one. We're going to get into the details
of this absolute minefield of a machine
in a second.
Let's get a spoon. It's just ice with
cherry syrup. So, yeah, this is
definitely snow cone. This is not shaved
ice. Okay, let's get into the review of
this machine. So, Viva sent me this
machine for independent
review. I'm going to unplug it.
Um, and oh, I've
used snow cone machines and ice shavers
for many, many years, and this is
possibly the worst one I've used. It
makes such a mess. It's quiet. I mean,
you got to give it that. It is quiet.
So, that's a positive.
The negative is number one,
the I'm going to keep tidying up because
I can't stand there being this much
mess. Having the gaps around this
plunger
here, it is no good because
it it just pushes that ice and that
water back out the side. So, that's
that's a terrible design that this thing
really irritates me here. It's like a
stop. It should be a stop, but it's not.
It's just super thin plastic rubber. The
hopper isn't big enough. So, it it's
it's big enough for maybe a two or three
person single scoop of this, if you
will,
serving, but that also means that it's
not very deep, which is why it comes
flying out the front. Second, there's no
capture device after you've removed that
bowl. So once you've done it, you're
then going to be dishing up your
ice and it's going to be pouring water
all over the
countertop, which is just irritating.
And it just keeps dripping. So I'm going
to leave that bit of kitchen roll
there. The texture of the ice is very
much crushed. It's not shaved. It does
though. Um, it does keep its shape, but
that that will happen with any kind of
ice. So, it's crushed ice. It's not
shaved ice. That's a big disappointment
because on the website it says shaved
ice, too. Um, if this was shaved ice, it
would be much better. That's much more
appropriate for a small machine like
this. Having a ice crusher like this, it
it's useless because it's it goes
everywhere. I probably lost 30% of that
material all over the counter here.
Whilst I appreciate having this machine
sent to me, it's not very good. I don't
recommend this machine if you're just a
home user. There are much better home
userbased machines for this. And any of
those off-brand will actually have
better things like a capture tray for
your ice. So after you've done your
shaving and you've taken it out to dish
it up, you got nothing left under here.
All the other machines that are are
somewhat, you know, childish in design,
but that's kind of who they're aimed,
that's what the product is aimed
towards, let's be fair. They all have a
plastic capture tray. So, you know, drip
tray, if you will. So, even after you
take this out, you're not making a mess
all over your counter. This needs that.
That is it down here. It It needs a
plastic drip tray permanently built in
and that sits on top.
Um, texture-wise it's fine for snow
cone. Um, yeah, it the syrup it tastes
delicious cuz the syrup is lovely and
that's all it is, syrup and water. But
ultimately, I'm going to say if you want
to make snow cones, don't get this
machine. Uh, if for some reason you do
want this machine, I will put a link in
the description and all the information
needed to buy one of these. And before
we finish there, the one positive that
this machine has, actually there's two
positives. The two positives that this
machine has over the other off-brand
rather childish looking ones is number
one the speed at which it did that. So
it's really fast and the price. This was
this is 90 I think 90
Canadian. So super cheap. You know you
can get an off brandand one probably on
Facebook marketplace for a for a tenner.
But that aside, if you're buying brand
new, the childish ones can go into the
couple hundred range. So, super good
value for money, but not for me
personally. Anyway, you can do crushed
ice in a Ninja blender. Let's do that
now. So, this is a Ninja auto IQ
blender. Um, it's got a lot of Ninja
blenders have this setting on. Get some
ice in
here. Put the lid on.
I mean, there's literally ice all over
the floor or what is now water from that
fever machine. So, here we're going to
turn this on. And look, ice crush. It's
nice and easy. Let's turn that
on.
Done. If you use a normal setting to
crush ice, it just decimates it and then
it melts into liquid. use the ice crush
setting. It doesn't produce as much heat
because it does short blast. But what
you have left there
is this
is
proper shaved ice. The
color, the size, it it's just like snow.
That is shaved ice. And you can do it in
your in your Ninja blender without any
problems whatsoever. That is 20 times
better than the Viva ice
crusher/ shaver. It's an ice crusher.
This makes
beautiful. This is very much like
Hawaiian shaved ice. Is perfect. Much
nicer to eat. Very much like the
Hawaiian shaved ice. If you're going to
spend money on something to make these,
just buy one of these.
Use the ice crush setting. Fill up your
to-go plastic containers. You can get
you get two of those with one of these.
These are like $79. So cheaper than that
and you're good to go. You can just keep
going. You can make these. They're
perfect. I mean, they're not it's not
even melting fast because of the the
texture and the amount of air that's
incorporated into it. So, please do
yourself a favor.
If you want to make Hawaiian shaved ice,
Italian ice, go for one of these. Thanks
very much for watching. Big thanks to
Viva for allowing me to review the ice
crusher/shaver. Shame that it was
useless. Don't forget to like and
subscribe. Next week, I'm going to do a
video on Starbucks
Frappuccinos and then we're going to get
back to more ice cream. So, tata for
now.